Alice Weld Tallant Papers, 1896-1958
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Alice Weld Tallant Papers
1896-1958
Tallant, Alice Weld, 1875-1958
MS 158
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Physician, Settlement house worker, Relief worker, World War I. Small collection related to Tallant's medical career at Joy Settlement and St. Martha's House, Philadelphia, and in France during World War I.
Biographical Note
Alice Weld Tallant was born in Boston on 14 July 1875. She attended private schools, and earned her A.B. from Smith College in 1897 and her M.D. from Johns Hopkins in 1902. She did graduate work at the hospital of the New York Lying-In Society and later at the Charite Hospital in Berlin. She interned and assisted at New England Hospital for Women and Children in Boston from 1902 to 1905. Tallant worked as "Examiner for Gymnasium and Lecturer in Hygiene" at Bates College from 1903 to 1904. She was Professor of Obstetrics at the Women's Medical College of Pennsylvania and Obstetrician-in-Chief at College Hospital from 1905 to 1923. From 1922-28, she was an obstetrician at the Philadelphia General Hospital. She went overseas with the Smith College Relief Unit in World War I, serving from July 1917 until February 1918. While there, she served in the 6th French army military evacuation hospital and was awarded the Croix de Guerre in 1918. In 1922, she wrote a textbook on obstetrical nursing.
From 1905 until her death in 1958, Tallant practiced obstetrics at the Woman's Hospital in Philadelphia. In addition to these responsibilities, throughout her life she worked in other hospitals and institutions in Philadelphia, including the Baby's Hospital from 1924 to 1942. Tallant also served as physician and social worker at the Joy Settlement from 1928 to 1938, and contributed her time and expertise to the Girls' House of Refuge from 1906 to 1950, first as visiting physician and then as consulting physician. Alice Weld Tallant died 31 May 1958.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers include a small amount of material related to her medical career after graduation from Johns Hopkins University in 1902, at Joy Settlement and St. Martha's House, Philadelphia; and more extensive documentation of her work in France during World War I, both as Director of Smith College Relief Unit, and later in a French Army Hospital. Letters (1902-1957) to and from Tallant include those of her grandmother, playwright Alice Brown, and Sophia Smith Collection Director, Margaret Storrs Grierson. Also included are biographical materials, photographs, radio scripts, memorabilia, and tributes from the French government and citizens.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Alice Weld Tallant donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection circa 1947 to 1959.
Search Terms
Tallant, Alice Weld, 1875-1958; Smith College. Relief Unit--History--Sources; Social settlements--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia--History--Sources; Women physicians--Pennsylvania--Biography--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care--France; World War, 1914-1918--War work--France
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional material on Alice Weld Tallant is in the Smith College Archives.
Contents List
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Alice Brown to the Anthony family, 1915-47 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous from AWT (including accounts of relief work in France), 1902-58 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Alice Brown to AWT, 1896-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - AWT to Margaret Grierson, 1946-1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biographical material, clippings, and memorabilia 1912-58, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - France
    - Smith College Relief Unit and medical relief work: correspondence, reports, photographs and memorabilia, 1917-18 [see also folder 3] (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - American Committee for Devastated France: correspondence, testimonials, medals and citations (including Croix de Guerre), 1918-19, [See also Oversized materials] (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Radio scripts, 1848, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Philadelphia County Medical Society: plaque, invitation, photograph and testimonials, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Writings by AWT: reprints and articles, 1915-26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Johns Hopkins Medical School: correspondence, 1955, [See also Awards and Oversized materials] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Poems, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, 1897-1920s, n.d. [see also folder 8] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Awards
    - Box of medals (Box 1)
    - Johns Hopkins University: Fifty Year Alumnus medal (Box 1)
- OVERSIZED MATERIALS
  - Johns Hopkins University medical diploma, 1902 (Map-case Flat File)
  - Americain pour les regions devastees de la France: licenses and certificate, 1916-1923 (Map-case Flat File)